<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay to revive the antient education of gentlewomen in religion, manners, arts &amp; tongues with an answer to the objections against this way of education.</title>
            <title>Essay to revive the antient education of gentlewomen, in religion, manners, arts &amp; tongues</title>
            <author>Makin, Bathsua, fl. 1612-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51611</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M309</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8034</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12639306</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12639306</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64990</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51611)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64990)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 697:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay to revive the antient education of gentlewomen in religion, manners, arts &amp; tongues with an answer to the objections against this way of education.</title>
                  <title>Essay to revive the antient education of gentlewomen, in religion, manners, arts &amp; tongues</title>
                  <author>Makin, Bathsua, fl. 1612-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D., to be sold by Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Education.</term>
               <term>Education --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64990:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64990:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY To Revive the Antient Education OF Gentlewomen, IN
Religion, Manners, Arts &amp; Tongues. WITH An Anſwer to the Objections
againſt this Way of Education.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> to be ſold by
<hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Bible and Crown at the lower end of
<hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64990:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64990:2"/>
            <head>To all Ingenious and Vertuous Ladies, more eſpecially to her
Highneſs the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy MARY, Eldeſt Daughter to his Royal Highneſs the Duke
of YORK.</head>
            <p>CUſtom, when it is inveterate, hath a mighty influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: it hath
the force of Nature it ſelf. The Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous cuſtom to breed Women low, is
grown general amongſt us, and hath prevailed ſo far, that it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
believed (eſpecially amongſt a ſort of debauched Sots) that Women are not
endued with ſuch Reaſon, as Men; nor capable of improvement by Education,
as they are. It is lookt upon as a monſtrous thing, to pretend the contrary.
A Learned Woman is thought to be a Comet, that bodes Miſchief, when ever it
appears. To offer to the World the liberal Education of Women is to deface the
Image of God in Man, it will make Women ſo high, and men ſo low, like Fire
in the Houſe-top, it will ſet the whole world in a Flame.</p>
            <p>Theſe things and worſe then theſe, are commonly talked of,
and verily believed by many, who think themſelves wiſe Men: to contradict
theſe is a bold attempt; where the Attempter muſt expect to meet with much
oppoſition. Therefore, Ladyes, I beg the candid Opinion of your Sex, whoſe
Intereſt I aſſert. More eſpecially I implore the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of your Royal
Highneſs, a Perſon moſt Eminent amongſt them, whoſe Patronage alone
will be a ſufficient Protection. What I have written is not out of humour to
ſhew how much may be ſaid of a trivial thing to little purpoſe. I verily
think, Women were formerly Educated in the knowledge of Arts and Tongues, and
by their Education, many did riſe to a great height in Learning. Were Women
thus Educated now,<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64990:3"/>I am confident the advantage would be very
great: The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men would have Honour and Pleaſure, their Relations Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,
and the whole Nation Advantage. I am very ſenſible it is an ill time to
ſet on foot this Deſign: wherein not only Learning but Vertue it ſelf is
ſcorn'd and neglected, as pedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick things, fit only for the Vulgar. I know
no better way to reform theſe Exorbitancies, than to perſwade Women to
ſcorn thoſe Toyes and Trifles, they now ſpend their time about, and to
attempt higher things, here offered: This will either reclaim the Men; or make
them aſhamed to claim the Sovereignty over ſuch as are more Wiſe and
Vertuous than themſelves.</p>
            <p>Were a competent number of Schools erected to Educate Ladyes
ingenuouſly, methinks I ſee how aſham'd Men would be of their Ignorance,
and how induſtrious the next Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would be to wipe off their
Reproach.</p>
            <p>I expect to meet with many Scoffes and Taunts from
incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate and illiterate Men, that prize their own Luſts and
Pleaſure more than your Profit and Content. I ſhall be the leſs concern'd
at theſe, ſo long as I am in your favour; and this diſcourſe may be a
Weapon in your hands to defend your ſelves, whilſt you endeavour to
poliſh your Souls, that you may glorify God, and anſwer the end of your
Creation, to be meet helps to your Husbands. Let not your Ladiſhips be
of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, that I do not (as ſome have wittily done) plead for Female
Preeminence. To ask too much is the way to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied all. God hath made the
Man the Head, if you be edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and inſtructed, as I propoſe, I am ſure
you will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, and be ſatisfied that you are helps, that your
Husbands do conſult and adviſe with you. (which if you be wiſe they will
be glad of) and that your Husbands have the caſting-Voice, in whoſe
determinations you will acquieſce. That this may be the effect of this
Education in all Ladyes that ſhall attempt it, is the deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64990:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>I Hope I ſhall not need to beg the patience of Ladyes to
peruſe this Pamphlet: I have beſpoken, and do expect your Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage;
becauſe it is your Cauſe I plead againſt an ill cuſtom, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to
you, which Men will not willingly ſuffer to be broken. I would deſire Men
not to prejudge and caſt aſide this Book upon the ſight of the Title. If
I have ſolidly prov'd, what I do pretend to, and fairly anſwered the
Objections brought againſt my Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and if I have propoſed
ſomething that may be profitable to Man-kind, let it not be rejected. If this
way of Educating La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhould (as its like, it never will) be generally
practiſed, the greateſt hurt, that I fore-ſee, can enſue, is, to put
your Sons upon greater diligence to advance themſelves in Arts and Languages;
that they may be Superior to Women in Parts as well as in Place. This is the
great thing I deſigne. I am a Man my ſelf, that would not ſuggeſt a
thing prejudicial to our Sex. To propoſe Women rivals with us to Learning,
will make us court <hi>Minerva</hi> more heartily, leſt they ſhould be more
in Her Favour. I do verily think this to be the beſt way to diſpell the
Clouds of Ignorance, and to ſtop the Flouds of Debauchery, that the next
Generation may be more wiſe and vertuous than any of their Predeceſſours.
It is an eaſie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to quibble and droll upon a ſubject of this nature,
to ſcoff at Women kept ignorant, on purpoſe to be made ſlaves. This
ſavours not at all of a Manly Spirit, to trample upon thoſe that are down.
I forbid Scoffing and Scolding. Let any think themſelves agrieved, and come
forth fairly into the Field againſt this feeble Sex, with ſolid Arguments
to refute what I have aſſerted, I think I may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to be their
Champion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64990:4"/>
            <p>Theſe for my much Honoured and worthy Friend,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Have heard you diſcourſe of the Education of Gentlewomen
in Arts and Tongues. I wonder any ſhould think of ſo vain a thing.</p>
                  <p>Women do not much deſire Knowledge; they are of low parts,
ſoft fickle natures, they have other things to do they will not mind if they
be once Bookiſh; The end of Learning is to fit one for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Employment,
which Women are not capable of. <hi>Women muſt not ſpeak in the
Church,</hi> its againſt cuſtom. Solomon's good Houſe-wife is not
commended for Arts and Tongues, but for looking after her Servants; And that
which is worſt of all, they are of ſuch ill natures, they will abuſe
their Education, and be ſo intolerably Proud, there will be no living with
them: If all theſe things could be anſwered, they would not have
leiſure.</p>
                  <p>We ſend our Sons to School ſeven years, and yet not above
one in five get ſo much of the Tongues only, ſo as to keep them, and
nothing of Arts.</p>
                  <p>Girls cannot have more than half the time allotted them. If they
were capable, and had time, I cannot imagine what good it would do them. If it
would do them good, where ſhould they be Inſtructed. Their converſe with
Boyes would do them more hurt than all their Learning would do them good.</p>
                  <p>I have no prejudice againſt the Sex, but would gladly have a
fair anſwer to theſe things, or elſe ſhall breed up my Daughters as our
fore-fathers did.</p>
                  <p>Sir your Condeſcenſion herein will very much oblige,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your affectionate Friend.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>May 29. 1673.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:64990:4"/>
            <div type="section">
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſhould be the earneſt Endeavour of all men, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy
their Lives to thoſe noble, and excellent Ends, for which the Omnipotent and
all-wiſe Creatour made them, which are, the Glory of God, the Eternal
Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of their immortal Souls, and to be uſeful in their Places. One
generation paſſeth away, and an other cometh: But the Earth, the Theatre on
which we act, abideth for ever. All the Works of the Children of Men do remain,
not only in reſpect of the preſent and future Emolument or Detriment,
cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by them; But alſo in Reference to the Influence they have as
examples on ſucceeding Ages. The harveſt of Bliſs or Woe, will be
according to the Seed-time of this Life. This Life proceeds ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as it
begins, 
<q> 
                     <l>Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens ſervabit Odorem</l> 
                     <l>Teſta diu —</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>So great is the Force of the firſt Tincture any thing takes,
whether good, or bad. As Plants in Gardens excel thoſe, that grow wild; or as
Brutes, by due Management (Witneſs the Philoſophers Dogs) are much altered:
So Men, by liberal Education, are much better'd, as to intellectuals and
morals. All conclude great Care ought to be taken of the Males: But your doubt
in your Letter is concerning the Females. I think the greater Care ought to be
taken of Them: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Evil ſeems to be begun here, as in <hi>Eve,</hi>
and to be propagated by her Daughters. When the Sons of God took unto
themſelves the Daughters of Men, Wickedneſs multiplied apace. It was the
cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Counſel of <hi>Balaam</hi> to debauch <hi>Iſrael</hi> by
<hi>Balack's</hi> Idolatrous Women. Wretched <hi>Jezebel</hi> excites
<hi>Ahab</hi> to greater Wickedneſs, than he could ever have thought of. God
gave ſtrict Command to the Iſraelites, not to marry with heatheniſh
Women, When <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf (the wiſeſt of Men) did this, they
ſoon drew his Heart from God. Bad Women, weak to make Reſiſtance, are
ſtrong to tempt to evil: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without all Doubt great Care ought to be
taken, timely to ſeaſon them with Piety and Virtue.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:64990:5"/>your great Queſtion is, Whether to breed up
Women in Arts and Tongues, is not a mere new Device, never before practiſed
in the World. This you doubt the more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Becauſe Women are of low Parts,
and not capable of Improvement by this Education. If they could be improved,
you doubt, whether it would benefit them? If it would benefit them, you enquire
where ſuch Education may be had? or, whether they muſt go to School with
Boys? to be made twice more impudent than learned. At laſt you muſter up a
Legion of Objections.</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſpeak diſtinctly to your Queſtions, and then
anſwer your Objections.</p>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Women have formerly been educated in Arts and
Tongues.</head>
                  <p>Little is recorded concerning the manner, how Women were
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducated formerly: You can expect my Proof to be only topical and by
Circumſtances.</p>
                  <p>It doth appear out of Sacred Writ, that Women were imployed in
moſt of the great Tranſactions that happened in the World, even in
reference to Religion. <hi>Miriam</hi> ſeems to be next to <hi>Moſes</hi>
and <hi>Aaron,</hi> ſhe was a great Poet, and Philoſopher: For both
Learning, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion were generally in former times wrapt up in Verſe.</p>
                  <p>The Women met <hi>David,</hi> ſinging triumphant Songs,
compoſed (it's like by themſelves) a great Specimen of liberal
Education.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deborah,</hi> the Deliverer of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was
without all doubt a learned Woman, that underſtood the Law. <hi>Huldah</hi>
the Propheteſs, dwelt in a Colledge, (we may ſuppoſe) where Women were
trained up in good Literature. We may be ſure ſhe was a very wiſe Woman:
For King <hi>Joſiah</hi> ſends <hi>Hilkiah</hi> the Prieſt, and the
Nobles of his Court, in a Caſe of Difficulty and Danger, to conſult with
her. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 34.20.21 &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>In the New Teſtament we find <hi>Anna</hi> a
Propheteſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 16.1. Commends unto them <hi>Phebe,</hi>
who was not only a Servant of Chriſt: But a Servant of the Church at
<hi>Cencrea.</hi> Ver. 12. He tells us <hi>Triphena, Triphoſa</hi> and
<hi>Perſis</hi> laboured much in the Lord. <hi>Priſcilla</hi> inſtructed
<hi>Apollos.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Timothy's</hi> Grandmother called <hi>Lois,</hi> and his
Mother <hi>Eunice</hi> were not only Gracious Women, but learned Women; for
from a Child they inſtructed him in the holy Scriptures. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.
compared with <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.15. The Children of the Elect Lady, found
walking in the Truth, were inſtructed by her. <hi>Philips</hi> four Daughters
were Propheteſſes, <hi>Acts</hi> 21. Though Women may not ſpeak in the
Church;<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64990:5"/>yet thoſe extraordinarily inabled, to whom
<hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.5. might: For <hi>Paul</hi> directs
them they ſhould not pray nor propheſie with their Heads uncovered, which
ſuppoſes they might do the things. I ſhall not diſpute theſe Texts
what this praying and propheſying was; it ſerves my Turn, that Women
extraordinarily inabled, were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly imployed.</p>
                  <p>We may infer from the Stories of the Muſes, that this way of
Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation was very ancient. All conclude the <hi>Heroes</hi> were men famous
in their Generation, therefore canonized after their Deaths. We may with like
Reaſon conclude, <hi>Minerva</hi> and the nine Muſes were Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men famous for
Learning whilſt they lived, and therefore thus ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red when dead.</p>
                  <p>There is no Queſtion the <hi>Greeks</hi> and
<hi>Romans,</hi> when moſt flouriſhing, did thus educate their Daughters:
in Regard ſo many amongſt them were famous for Learning. As <hi>Sempronia,
Cornelia, Lelia, Mutia, Cleobulina, Caſſandra, Terentia, Hortenſia,
Sulpitia, Portia, Helvigia, Enonia, Paula, Albina, Pella, Zenobia, Valeria,
Proba, Eudocia, Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> and many others.</p>
                  <p>The Sybills could never have invented the Heroick, nor
<hi>Sappho</hi> the Sapphick Verſes, had they been illiterate. Do you think
<hi>Corinna</hi> could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have thrice out done <hi>Pindar,</hi> upon a
ſolemn Conteſt ſo excellent in his Lyrick Verſes, that none elſe
durſt imitate him, had ſhe not been inſtructed in Arts?</p>
                  <p>There was a Conteſt between twenty Grecian and twenty Roman
Ladies, which were moſt excellent in Learning. The Romane Dames were the
beſt Oratours: But the Grecian Ladies the beſt Philoſophers. This plainly
ſhews they both were inſtructed in all kind of good Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Women Educated in Arts and Tongues, have been eminent in
them.</head>
                  <p>I ſhould be too tedious, if I ſhould commemorate all upon
Record, that have been Smatterers in Learning. I ſhall only mention ſome
few Ladies that have been equal to moſt Men.</p>
                  <p>It is reported of <hi>Zenobia</hi> Queen of <hi>Palmeria,</hi>
that ſhe was not only excellent her ſelf in Arts and Arms: But Learning in
her (like light in the Sun) influenced her whole People, only famous in her
Daies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Olympia Fulnia Maurata,</hi> Tutreſs to the Empreſs of
<hi>Germany,</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>French, Latin, Dutch;</hi> ſhe was ſo
good a <hi>Grecian,</hi> that ſhe read<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64990:6"/>publick Lectures in
that Language. She was alſo reputed to be well skilled in Divinity.</p>
                  <p>The Lady <hi>Jane Grey</hi> excelled <hi>Maurata</hi> in this,
ſhe underſtood the <hi>Hebrew</hi> alſo. There is a large Diſcourſe
of her Learning (in which ſhe took great delight) and Piety, in the Book of
Martyrs.</p>
                  <p>The preſent Dutcheſs of <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> by her own
Genius, rather than any timely Inſtruction, over-tops many grave
Gown-Men.</p>
                  <p>I am forbidden to mention the Counteſs <hi>Dowager</hi> of
<hi>Huntington</hi> (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed ſometimes by Mrs. <hi>Makin</hi>) how well
ſhe underſtands <hi>Latin, Greek, Hebrew, French</hi> and
<hi>Spaniſh;</hi> or what a proficient ſhe is in Arts, ſubſervient to
Divinity, in which (if I durſt I would tell you) ſhe excels.</p>
                  <p>The Princeſs <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> daughter to King
<hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, to whom Mrs. <hi>Makin</hi> was Tutreſs, at
nine Years old could write, read, and in ſome meaſure underſtand,
<hi>Latin, Greek, Hebrew, French</hi> and <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> Had ſhe lived,
what a Miracle would She have been of her Sex!</p>
                  <p>The Princeſs <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> eldeſt Daughter to the
Queen of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> yet living, is verſed in all ſorts of choice
Literature.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. <hi>Thorold,</hi> Daughter of the Lady <hi>Car</hi> in
Lincolnſhire, was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in Philoſophy, and all ſorts of
Learning.</p>
                  <p>I cannot without Injury forget the Lady <hi>Mildmay,</hi> and
Dr. <hi>Loves</hi> Daughters; Their Worth and Excellency in Learning is yet
freſh in the Memory of many Men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cornelia</hi> read publick Philoſophy-Lectures at
<hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe brought up her Sons, the <hi>Gracchi,</hi> ſo, that they
were the only Men famous in their Dayes. She was admired by <hi>Cicero</hi> for
diverſe of her Works.</p>
                  <p>The Papal Chair could not defend it ſelf, but was invaded by
a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for her Excellency in Learning above the men of her Times; As
<hi>Volateran, Sigebertus, Platina</hi> and others, that have writ the Lives of
the Roman Biſhops, do declare. She is remembred likewiſe to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
by <hi>Boccaſius</hi> in his Book <hi>de Claris Mulieribus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Roſuida,</hi> a Saxon by Nation, She lived under
<hi>Lotharius the firſt;</hi> She was Eloquent in the <hi>Greek</hi> and
<hi>Roman</hi> Tongues, and practiſed in all good Arts. She compoſed many
Works, not without great commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Readers. One to exhort to
Chaſtity, Virtue, and Divine Worſhip. She publiſhed ſix
<hi>Comedies;</hi> beſides a noble Poem in <hi>Hexameter verſe,</hi> of the
Heroick Acts done by the <hi>Otho Ceſars;</hi> with divers others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Elizabetha</hi> of <hi>Schonaugia</hi> zealouſly
imitated the Study and Practice of this <hi>Roſuida.</hi> She writ many
things in the Latin Tongue; namely, a<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64990:6"/>Book intituled, <hi>A
Path to direct us the way to God;</hi> as alſo a Volumn of Learned
Epiſtles; with many other Books.</p>
                  <p>I cannot omit <hi>Conſtantia</hi> the Wife of <hi>Alexander
Sforza;</hi> She was ſo Learned, that upon the ſuddain and without any
premeditation She was able ſufficiently to diſcourſe upon any Argument,
either Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, or Philoſophical: Beſides, She was very frequent in
the works of St. <hi>Hierome, Ambroſe, Gregory, Cicero,</hi> and
<hi>Lactantius.</hi> She was much admired for her Extempory vaine in Verſe.
Her Daughter <hi>Baptiſta</hi> was equal to Her in Fame and Merit, and was
reckoned among the beſt Learned, and moſt Illuſtrious Women.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſtina</hi> late Queen of <hi>Sweden</hi>
underſtood ſeveral Languages, and was well verſed in Politicks, and
acquainted with moſt Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</p>
                  <p>I thought of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> firſt, but purpoſely
mention Her laſt, as the Crown of all. How learned She was, the World can
teſtifie. It was uſual for her to diſcourſe with Forraign Agents in
their own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages. Mr. <hi>Aſcam,</hi> her Tutor, uſed to ſay, She
read more <hi>Greek</hi> in a day then many of the Doctors of her time did
<hi>Latin</hi> in a week. You ſee ſome Women have been good Proficients in
moſt kinds of Learning. I ſhall now ſhew you how they have been excellent
in ſome particular parts of it, as the <hi>Tongues, Oratory, Philoſophy,
Divinity,</hi> and laſtly <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etry.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Women have been good Linguiſts.</head>
                  <p>It is objected againſt Women, as a reproach, that they have
too much Tongue: but it's no crime they have many Tongues; if it be, many Men
would be glad to be guilty of that fault. The Tongue is the only Weapon Women
have to defend themſelves with, and they had need to uſe it dextrouſly.
Many ſay one tongue is enough for a Woman: it is but a quibble upon the word.
Several Languages, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by a Woman, will do our Gentlemen little hurt,
who have little more than their Mother-Wit, and underſtand only their
Mother-Tongue: theſe moſt uſually make this Objection, to hide their own
Ignorance. Tongues are learnt in order to Things. As things were, and yet are
in the World, its requiſite we learn Tongues to underſtand Arts: It's
therefore a Commendation to theſe Women after menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, that they were
Miſtreſſes of Tongues.</p>
                  <p>There is an ancient Copy of the Septuagent, ſent from the
Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of <hi>Alexandria</hi> to King <hi>James,</hi> written by a Woman
called <hi>Tecla,</hi> ſo accurate and excellent, that the Authors of the
Polyglot-Bible choſe<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64990:7"/>it before all other Copies written or
printed, to make uſe of in that Impreſſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anna Maria Schurman</hi> of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> (called by
<hi>Spanhemius, ultimum Naturae in hôc ſexu conatum, et decimam
Muſam,</hi> Natures Maſter-piece amongſt Women, excelling the very
Muſes) hath printed divers Works in <hi>Latin, Greek, French</hi> and the
<hi>Perſian</hi> Tongue; ſhe underſtood the <hi>Arabick</hi> alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
Beſides, ſhe was an excellent Poet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amalaſuntha</hi> Queen of the <hi>Oſtrogothes,</hi>
the Daughter of <hi>Theodericus,</hi> was a great Miſtreſs of the Latin and
Greek Tongues, ſhe ſpake di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly all the barbarous Languages that
were uſed in the Eaſtern Empires.</p>
                  <p>For Excellency in Tongues moſt of thoſe Perſons before
mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned are eminent Inſtances, <hi>Maurata,</hi> the Lady <hi>Jane
Grey,</hi> and the three <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Women have not been meer Talkers: (as ſome frivolous Men
would make them) but they have known how to uſe Languages, when they have had
them. Many Women have been excellent Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Women have been good Oratours.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> tell us of <hi>Ameſia</hi> a
modeſt Roman Lady, when ſhe was accuſed of a great Crime, and ready to
incur the Sentence of the Pretor, ſhe in a great Confluence ſtept up
amongſt the People, and without any Advocate pleaded her own Cauſe ſo
effectually, that by the publique Suffrage ſhe was acquitted from all
Aſperſion whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and from that Time ſhe was called
<hi>Androgine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hortenſia</hi> was equal to her, the Daughter of
<hi>Quintus Hortenſius.</hi> When a greivous Fine was impoſed upon the
Roman Matrons by the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunes, when all Lawyers and Oratours were afraid to
take upon them the Patronage of their Cauſe, this diſcreet Lady pleaded
before the Triumvirate in the behalf of the Women, ſo happily and boldly,
that the greateſt Part of the Mulct impoſed upon them, was remitted.</p>
                  <p>Some have commended <hi>Caia Affricana's</hi> Eloquence: I
cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the Uſe ſhe put it to, but paſs her over.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tullia</hi> (by the Inſtruction of her Mother
<hi>Terentia</hi>) was counted e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to her Father <hi>Cicero</hi> in
Eloquence.</p>
                  <p>Divers of thoſe Perſons before mentioned were very
eloquent, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly <hi>Maurata, Cornelia,</hi> and Queen
<hi>Elizabeth.</hi> We may ſuppoſe <hi>Schurman,</hi> and the reſt that
wrote ſo elegantly, could alſo ſpeak elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently upon a juſt
occaſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64990:7"/>It is objected againſt poor Women, they
may learn Tongues and ſpeak freely, being naturally diſpoſed to be
talkative: But for any ſolid Judgment or depth of Reaſon, it is ſeldom
found in their giddy Crowns. I proceed therefore to ſhew they have been good
<hi>Logicians, Philoſophers, Mathematicians, Divines,</hi> and
<hi>Poets.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Women have underſtood Logick.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Logick</hi> is the Key, thoſe that have this in their
Heads may unlock o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sciences; ſome Women have had it at their Girdles,
and been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dextrous in Diſputation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hipparchia</hi> with one <hi>Sophiſm</hi> put to Silence
<hi>Theodorus.</hi> It was thus: That which <hi>Theodorus</hi> doing, he is not
ſaid to do unjuſtly; if <hi>Hippar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia</hi> do, ſhe is not ſaid to do
unjuſtly. This he granted. She proceeds, But, <hi>Theodorus</hi> beating
himſelf, is not ſaid to do unjuſtly; therefore if <hi>Hipparchia</hi>
beat <hi>Theodorus,</hi> ſhe is not ſaid to do unjuſtly.
<hi>Theodorus</hi> makes no Reply, but, juſt like our lazy Gentlemen, goes
out of the Room and ſaith, <hi>Let Women mind their Spinning.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Margarita Sorocchia,</hi> a Gentlewoman of <hi>Rome,</hi>
is lookt upon as ſo great a Sopiſter, that ſhe is ordinarily a Moderatix
in the Academy at the Diſputation amongſt learned Wits, in the moſt
Polite Parts of Learning and Philoſophy, yea and Divinity too.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe who read <hi>Schurman</hi>'s Decertations, will
conclude ſhe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the Principles and Practice of Logick very
well.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caecilia</hi> did ſtrange things by her great Skill in
Logick, particularly by ſolid Argument, ſhe diſwaded <hi>Tiburtius
Valerianus</hi> his Brother, from heatheniſh Idolatry to the Chriſtian
Faith.</p>
                  <p>Some think I have hardly ſpoke to the Purpoſe yet; Logick
diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to wrangle, a thing Women are inclined to naturally: I proceed
therefore to ſhew that Women have been great Proficients in the moſt
ſolid Parts of Learning, which require moſt ſerious Thoughts and
greateſt Judgment; they have been good Philoſophers, good Arithmetici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
good Divines, and good Poets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Women have been profound <hi>Philoſophers.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>That they have been good <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> appears from
thoſe numerous examples before mentioned. I ſhould but tautologize to
repeat them again. Take only their names; <hi>Roſuida, Elizabeth</hi> of
<hi>Schonaugia, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia,</hi> her Daughter <hi>Baptiſta, Anna Maria
Schurman, Margarita So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racchia,</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64990:8"/>&amp;c. All thoſe
hereafter mentioned as eminent in Divinity, muſt needs have ſome competent
skill in <hi>Philoſophy;</hi> as <hi>Tibiola, Marcella, Euſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium,</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aganolda</hi> was ſo deſirous of knowledge, that ſhe
put her ſelf into mans Apparel, attained ſo great a perfection in Natural
<hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and in the practice of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> that ſhe
was envied by all thoſe of her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, and ſlandered for incontinency; to
vindicate her ſelf, ſhe diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhe was a Woman.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Miriam</hi> was a great <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> and ſo
was the Queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi> or elſe ſhe would never have ventured to
try the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon</hi> in dark Problems, and by hard
Queſtions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nicoſtrata</hi> (by ſome called <hi>Carmentis</hi>)
helped to make up the <hi>Greek</hi> Alphabet, and made ſome addition to the
<hi>Roman</hi> Letters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aſpaſia,</hi> a <hi>Mileſian</hi> Damſel, was ſo
learned, that ſhe inſtructed <hi>Pericles,</hi> and of a great Souldier,
made him an excellent <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> and one of the beſt Orators in
<hi>Greece,</hi> and after was married to him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Socrates</hi> acknowledges he imitated
<hi>Aſpaſia</hi> in his <hi>Facultas Politica,</hi> and doth not bluſh to
call <hi>Diotima</hi> his Tutreſs. Theſe two Women were ſo learned, as to
teach this great <hi>Philoſopher.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arete</hi> attained to that perfection in
<hi>Philoſophy,</hi> that ſhe inſtructed her ſon <hi>Ariſtippus,</hi>
who was therefore called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taught. After her Fathers death, ſhe erected a School of
<hi>Philoſophy,</hi> where ſhe commonly read to a full and frequent
Auditory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Leontinum,</hi> a <hi>Grecian</hi> Damſel, was ſo well
ſeen in <hi>Philoſophical</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, that ſhe feared not to
write a Book againſt the worthy <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dama,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and her
Mother, were excellent <hi>Philoſophers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pythagoras</hi> profeſſes he often adviſed with, and
received help from <hi>Themiſtoclea.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhould be too troubleſom to you, if I ſhould ſpeak
particularly of the Learning of <hi>Adeſia,</hi> the Wiſdom of
<hi>Hermodica,</hi> the Improvement of <hi>Themiſte</hi> in
<hi>Pythagorean</hi> Philoſophy, of the Works of <hi>Genebria,</hi> or how
eloquent the two Daughters of L. <hi>Craſſus</hi> were.</p>
                  <p>I had almoſt ſorgotten <hi>Chriſtina</hi> Queen of
<hi>Sweden</hi> in Philology and Philoſophy, ſuperior to moſt of the
great Scholars in Europe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Portia, Cato</hi>'s Daughter, was the beſt Philoſopher
in her Time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64990:8"/>
                  <head>Some Women have underſtood the
<hi>Mathematicks.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The <hi>Mathematicks</hi> require as much ſeriouſneſs as
any Art or Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, yet ſome Women have attained an extraordinary knowledge
in theſe alſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hyppatia</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> Daughter of
<hi>Theon,</hi> writ of Aſtronomy; ſhe was Profeſſor in the School in
<hi>Alexandria,</hi> where ſhe was frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by many worthy Scholars.
Afterwards by ſuch as envied her Fame for Learning, ſhe was pitifully
ſlain and maſſacred.</p>
                  <p>A Lady of late, I have forgot her name, is ſo well skilled
in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicks, that ſhe hath printed divers Tables.</p>
                  <p>If any think all this Learning is but meerly humane, I
acknowledge the great end of Arts and Tongues is the better to enable us to
know God in Jeſus Chriſt, and our own ſelves, that we may glorifie and
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy him for ever.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <l>Si Chriſtum diſeis, nil eſt ſi caetera ouſeis.</l>

                     <l>Si Chriſtum neſeis, nil eſt ſi caetera
diſcis.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Many Women have improved their humane Knowledge, ſo as by
Gods Bleſſing hath been a means of their obtaining Spiritual Knowledg.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fabiola,</hi> a Roman Matron, had attained ſo great
Perfection in the Knowledge of the Scriptures, that ſhe had a reverent
Reſpect from the Learned in her Time. St. <hi>Jerome</hi> vouchſafed to
dedicate a Book to her intituled <hi>de Veſta Sacerdotali.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marcella,</hi> a Roman, was ſo eminent in the Knowledge
of Divinity, that St. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſalutes her by Name in many of his
Epiſtles. He writ diverſe Books to her. One <hi>de Mundi contemptu;</hi>
another of the ten Names God is called by amongſt the Hebrews; a Third of
Faith; a Fourth of Blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt; And diverſe
others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Euſtochium,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Paula,</hi> a Roman
Matron, was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a Divine, and ſo well practiſed in the
<hi>Scriptures,</hi> and in the <hi>Greek, Latin,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi>
Dialects, that ſhe was called the new Prodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of the World.</p>
                  <p>We may reflect upon diverſe of thoſe before mentioned to
ſupply the Defect of Examples in this Place. Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and
the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Jane Grey</hi> were eminent for their Knowledge in Religion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Roſuida, Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>Schonaugia,
Conſtantia</hi> the Wife of <hi>Alexander Sforza,</hi> and her Daughter
<hi>Baptiſta,</hi> were excellent in Divinity as well as Philoſophy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64990:9"/>The Works of <hi>Anna Maria Schurman,</hi>
that are extant, declare how good a Divine ſhe was.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall conclude with <hi>Iſola Navarula,</hi> who writ
many eloquent Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. She was a great proficient in Philoſophy and
Theology, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by that Book ſhe wrote by way of Dialogue, between
<hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> which ſinned firſt and moſt; and by
divers other Books.</p>
                  <p>There is one thing yet remaining, in which Women have
excelled, that is, <hi>Poetry.</hi> Their excellency in this, tends as much to
their vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation as any thing yet ſpoken to. To be a <hi>Poetaſter,</hi>
is no great matter; but to be a <hi>Poet-laureat,</hi> requires great natural
endowments, ſuch as man cannot lend, if God doth not give; <hi>Poeta
naſcitur, non fit.</hi> If a man's natural parts be low, Induſtry,
Education, Time, and Practice, may raiſe to ſome competent height in
Oratory; therefore we ſay, <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor fit:</hi> But all the Inſtruction
and Education in the World, all the pains, time, and patience imaginable, can
never infuſe that ſublime Fancy, that ſtrong Memory, and excellent
Judgment required in one that ſhall wear the Bayes. If Women have been good
Poets, Men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure them exceedingly, to account them giddy-headed Goſſips,
fit only to diſcourſe of their Hens, Ducks, and Geeſe, and not by any
means to be ſuffered to meddle with Arts and Tongues, leſt by intollerable
pride they ſhould run mad.</p>
                  <p>If I do make this appear, that Women have been good Poets, it
will confirm all I have ſaid before: for, beſides natural Endowments, there
is required a general and univerſal improvement in all kinds of Learning. A
good Poet, muſt know things Divine, things Natural, things Moral, things
Hiſtorical, and things Artificial; together with the ſeveral terms
belonging to all Faculties, to which they muſt allude. Good Poets muſt be
univerſal Scholars, able to uſe a pleaſing Phraſe, and to expreſs
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with moving Eloquence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Women have been good Poets.</head>
                  <p>Becauſe ſo much depends upon this, I beg the Mens
patience, if I be a little tedious on this Point. I queſtion not the Women
will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to hear their Sex vindicated.</p>
                  <p>I begin with <hi>Minerva,</hi> the Goddeſs of Wiſdom;
ſhe was for no other reaſon reckoned amongſt the Goddeſſes, but for
her excellency and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in Poetry and other good Arts, of which ſhe is
ſaid to be the firſt Inventreſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:64990:9"/>There were three <hi>Corinna</hi>'s, famous
for Poetry. One lived in the time of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and was very dear to
<hi>Ovid.</hi> A ſecond was called <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinna Theſpia,</hi> ſhe is
celebrated in the Books of the Antient Poets, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Statius.</hi>
The third, and moſt eminent, was <hi>Corinna Thebana;</hi> ſhe was Daughter
of <hi>Archelodorus</hi> and <hi>Procratia,</hi> and Scholar to
<hi>Myrtis.</hi> In five ſet Conteſts ſhe bore away the Palm from
<hi>Pindar,</hi> Prince of the Lyrick Poets. She publiſhed five Books of
Excellent Epigrams.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Erinna,</hi> Sir-named <hi>Teia,</hi> or (as ſome will
have it) <hi>Telia,</hi> from the Iſland <hi>Telos,</hi> not far diſtant
from <hi>Gnidon;</hi> ſhe flouriſhed in the time of <hi>Dion</hi> of
<hi>Syracuſa,</hi> and publiſhed an excellent Poem in the <hi>Dorick</hi>
Tongue, beſides divers Epigrams. Her Stile was ſaid to come near the
Majeſty of <hi>Homer</hi>'s. She died when ſhe was but nineteen years of
Age.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sappho,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Scamandaurus,</hi> lived
in the time of <hi>Tarqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Priſcus;</hi> ſhe firſt deviſed the
<hi>Sapphick</hi> Verſe, and found out the uſe of the Harp with a Quill.
There was alſo another <hi>Sappho</hi> called <hi>Mitele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> who lived
long after. She publiſhed many rare and famous Poems amongſt the
<hi>Greeks;</hi> and therefore had the honour to be called the <hi>tenth
Muſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Proba Valeria Falcona,</hi> a Roman Matron, lived in the
time of <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius junior.</hi> She compoſed a
Divine Poem of the Life, Works, and Miracles of Chriſt. She alſo
Paraphraſed upon the Verſes of <hi>Homer,</hi> and called the Work
<hi>Homeroucheutra.</hi> Her Husband being dead, ſhe inſcribed upon his
Tomb an Epitaph, Engliſhed thus: 
<q> 
                        <l>To God, to Prince, Wife, Kindred, Friends, the Poor;</l> 
                        <l>Religious, Loyal, True, Kind, Stedfaſt, Dear,</l> 
                        <l>In Zeal, Faith, Love, Help, Amity, and Store;</l> 
                        <l>He, that ſo liv'd, and ſo deceas'd, lies
here.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I had almoſt forgot the <hi>Sybils:</hi> The Name
ſignifies ſuch as have thoughts of God. As a Man that propheſieth is
called a Prophet, ſo a Woman predicting, was called a <hi>Sybil.</hi> There
were twelve of theſe, all of them Poets. <hi>Sybilla Lybica</hi> invented the
<hi>Heroick</hi> Verſe. <hi>Sybilla Delphica</hi> was ſo famous a Poet,
that <hi>Homer</hi> did take many of her Verſes to himſelf, and made them
his own. All of them delivered their Oracles in Verſe: If their Verſes were
not ſo ſmooth as <hi>Homers</hi> and <hi>Heſiods,</hi> an abatement
muſt be made for the matter and manner of their ſpeaking, which was
uſually in an extaſie. They all propheſied of Chriſt. I ſhall
inſert only one or two of their Predictions, thus Engliſhed. 
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64990:10"/> 
                     <q> 
                        <l>A King, a Prieſt, a Prophet, all theſe three</l> 
                        <l>Shall meet in one; Sacred Divinity</l> 
                        <l>Shall be to Fleſh eſpous'd. O, who can ſcan</l> 
                        <l>This Myſtery, uniting God with Man!</l> 
                        <l>When this rare Birth into the World ſhall come,</l> 
                        <l>He the great God of Oracles ſtrikes dumb.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sybilla Delphica</hi> ſpeaks to this purpoſe. 
<q> 
                        <lg>
                           <l>An Angel ſhall deſcend, and ſay,</l>
                           <l>Thou bleſſed <hi>Mary</hi> hail;</l>
                           <l>Thou ſhalt conceive, bring forth, yet be</l>
                           <l>A Virgin without fail.</l>
                        </lg> 
                        <lg>
                           <l>Three Gifts the <hi>Chald'ans</hi> to thy Son</l>
                           <l>Shall tender with much pietie,</l>
                           <l>Myrrhe to a Man, Gold to a King,</l>
                           <l>And Incenſe to a Deitie.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall mention only one more, which is that of <hi>Sybilla
Europa.</hi> 
                     <q> 
                        <lg>
                           <l>When the great King of all the World ſhall have</l>
                           <l>No place on Earth by which he may be known;</l>
                           <l>When he that comes, all mortal men to ſave,</l>
                           <l>Shall find his own Life by the World o'rethrown.</l>
                           <l>When the moſt Juſt, injuſtice ſhall deprave,</l>
                           <l>And the great Judge be judged by his own.</l>
                        </lg> 
                        <lg>
                           <l>Death when to Death, a Death by Death hath given,</l>
                           <l>Then ſhall be op't the long-ſhut Gates of
Heaven.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I do not produce theſe as Foundations of our Faith; We have
a more ſure word of Propheſie which we ought to look unto, as a Light that
ſhineth in a dark place. This is more ſure than that which we ſee with
our Eyes, hear with our Ears, or handle with our Hands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:64990:10"/>
                     <hi>Cleobulina</hi> was Daughter of
<hi>Cleobulus Lindus,</hi> one of the ſeven Wiſe Men of <hi>Greece.</hi>
She imitated, and ſome think did equalize her Father. She was eminent for
<hi>Enigma</hi>'s and <hi>Riddles.</hi> Take this one rendred thus: 
<q> 
                        <l>One Father hath twelve Children great and ſmall,</l> 
                        <l>And they beget twice fifteen, Daughters all;</l> 
                        <l>Half of them White, half Black, immortal made;</l> 
                        <l>And yet we ſee how every hour they fade.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I cannot leave out <hi>Helpis,</hi> the Wife of the Famous
Philoſopher and Poet <hi>Boethius Severinus;</hi> becauſe many Hymns to the
Apoſtles are yet extant, which <hi>Gyraldus</hi> and the beſt Writers
conſtantly affirm to be hers. She writ her Epitaph with her own hand,
tranſlated thus; 
<q> 
                        <l>
                           <hi>Helpis</hi> my Name, me <hi>Sicily</hi> firſt
bred;</l> 
                        <l>A Husband's love drew me from hence to <hi>Rome,</hi>
                        </l> 
                        <l>Where I long liv'd in joy, but now lie dead,</l> 
                        <l>My Soul ſubmitting to th' Almighties doom.</l> 
                        <l>And I believe this fleſh again ſhall riſe,</l> 
                        <l>And I behold my Saviour with theſe eyes.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I may put <hi>Philenis</hi> and <hi>Aſteniſſa</hi>
together; they were both good Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, and imitated one another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hildegardis Moguntina</hi> was eminent for Learning and
Piety as well as Poetry: Her Works were approved in the Council held at
<hi>Tryers,</hi> where Dr. <hi>Bernard</hi> was preſent.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> ſpeaks much of <hi>Clitagora
Lacedemonia,</hi> and <hi>Serabo</hi> in his <hi>Homerica</hi> ſpeaks more of
<hi>Heſtia Alexandria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Antipater Theſſalus,</hi> gives the firſt place
amongſt the nine <hi>Lyric</hi> Poets, to <hi>Paxilla Syconia.</hi> She lived
in the thirty ſecond <hi>Olympiad.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhould be too tedious, if I ſhould give you a particular
account what <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Michaele;</hi> what
<hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> of <hi>Gharixena;</hi> what <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> ſpeaks
of <hi>Muſea;</hi> or, what <hi>Textor</hi> remembers of <hi>Meroe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cornificina, Luccia Mima, Caſſandra,
Magaloſtrate,</hi> were good Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets. <hi>Polla Argentaria,</hi> Wife to the
famous Poet <hi>Lucan,</hi> was reputed of that excellent Learning, that ſhe
aſſiſted her Husband in the three firſt Books, entituled
<hi>Pharſalia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I can but name thoſe Poets <hi>Anyle, Noſiis, Myro
Byzantia, Damophila;</hi> becauſe I haſten to thoſe nearer our own times:
Only take notice, theſe<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64990:11"/>numerous Examples of Learned
Women, do plainly prove, they were heretofore liberally educated.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lorentia Stoza</hi> is now famous in <hi>Italy</hi> for
divers Hymns ſhe compoſed in divers kinds of Verſe, eſpecially in
excellent <hi>Sapphicks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How excellent a Poet Mrs. <hi>Broadſtreet</hi> is, (now in
<hi>America</hi>) her Works do teſtifie.</p>
                  <p>We need no other Encomium of Mris. <hi>Philips,</hi> than what
Mr. <hi>Cowley</hi> gives, he plucks the Lawrel from his own Brow, to crown
hers, as beſt deſerving it. Beſides, her Works in print ſpeak for
her.</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>John Harington</hi> in his Allegory upon the 37 Books
of <hi>Arioſta,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends unto us the four Daughters of Sir <hi>Anthony
Cook;</hi> alſo the Lady <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> the Lady <hi>Bacon,</hi> the
Lady <hi>Killegrew,</hi> giving to each of them, for Poetry, a worthy
Character; whither I refer the Reader.</p>
                  <p>In the ſame place the Author commends to us, a great
<hi>Italian</hi> Lady, <hi>Vittoria,</hi> who writ largely and learnedly in the
praiſe of her dead Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. With whom I may rank (if in the compariſon I
do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize) the beautiful and learned Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> Counteſs of
<hi>Pembrook,</hi> the worthy Siſter to that incomparable Perſon Sir
<hi>Philip Sidney.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lady <hi>Jane Gray,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Arabella,</hi>
had a great faculty in Poetry.</p>
                  <p>The two Orations delivered at the Univerſities by Queen
<hi>Elizabeth's</hi> own Mouth, gives ample teſtimony of her Oratory. Thoſe
ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fancies, and pleaſant Poems, bearing her Name, ſhews ſhe was a
good Poet.</p>
                  <p>The Lord <hi>Burghlies</hi> three Daughters were eminent for
Learning, and competent Poets; as appears by theſe Verſes made upon this
occaſion. <hi>Sileſia</hi> was in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> her Husband was
deſigned to be ſent Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor; <hi>Mildreda</hi> her Siſter was at
Court, who had intereſt there to hinder this intended Embaſſie of her
Brother; <hi>Sileſia</hi> writes to her Siſter <hi>Mildreda:</hi> 
                     <q> 
                        <l>Si mihi, quem cupio Dominum, <hi>Mildreda,</hi>
remittas,</l> 
                        <l>Tu bona, tu melior, tu mihi ſola Soror.</l> 
                        <l>Sin malè cunctando retines, vel trans Mare
mittas,</l> 
                        <l>Tu mala, tu pejor, tu mihi nulla Soror.</l> 
                        <l>At ſi <hi>Cornubiam,</hi> tibi pax ſit, &amp; omnia
laeta,</l> 
                        <l>Sin Mare, <hi>Sileſiae</hi> nuntio bella. Vale.</l> 
                     </q>

                     <q> 
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mildred,</hi> my Husband dear, if you now back do
ſend,</l> 
                        <l>Better than good you are, and Siſter to the end.</l> 
                        <l>
                           <pb n="21" facs="tcp:64990:11"/>But if you him ſtay there, or ſend
him o're the Sea,</l> 
                        <l>Much worſe than nought you are, no Siſter you ſhall
be.</l> 
                        <l>If <hi>Cornwal</hi> he does ſee, I'le pray, and all good
tell;</l> 
                        <l>But if he croſs the Sea, I am your foe.
Farewel.</l>
                     </q>
                     <bibl> Sileſia.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <p>It may now be demanded, by thoſe ſtudious of Antiquity,
why the Vertues, the Diſciplines, the Nine Muſes, the Deviſers, and
Patrons of all good Arts, the Three Graces; ſhould rather be repreſented
under the Feminine Sex, and their Pictures be drawn to the Portraictures of
Damoſels, and not have Maſculine Denominations, and the Effigies of Men?
Yea, why Chriſtians themſelves, in all their Books and Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings which they
commit to Poſterity, ſtill continue the ſame practice? Why Wiſdom is
ſaid to be the Daughter of the Higheſt, and not the Son? Why <hi>Faith,
Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> her Daughters, are repreſented as Women? Why
ſhould the ſeven Liberal Arts be expreſſed in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Shapes?
Doubtleſs this is one reaſon; Women were the Inventors of many of theſe
Arts, and the promoters of them, and ſince have ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed them, and attained
to an excellency in them: And being thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned and beautified with theſe
Arts, as a teſtimony of our gratitude for their Invention, and as a token of
honour for their Proficiency; we make Women the emblems of theſe things,
having no ſitter Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick to expreſs them by. I ſhall add this one
thing, worthy obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the great honour and commendation of the
Feminine Sex.</p>
                  <p>The parts of the World have their denomination from Women,
<hi>Aſia</hi> is ſo called from the Nymph <hi>Aſia,</hi> the Mother of
<hi>Japethus</hi> and <hi>Prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus. Europe,</hi> from <hi>Europa</hi> the
Daughter of <hi>Agenor. Lybia</hi> (which is <hi>Africa</hi>) from
<hi>Libia</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Epaphus. America</hi> (lately diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered)
bears the ſame Female Figure.</p>
                  <p>It is uſual for men to pride and boaſt themſelves in the
Wiſdom, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and Riches of their Anceſtors; what wiſe Men their
Fore-fathers have been, what great things they have done, and what large
poſſeſſions they have had, when they themſelves are degenerated and
become Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, Cowardly, beggarly, debauched Sots.</p>
                  <p>I hope Women will make another uſe of what I have ſaid;
inſtead of claiming honour from what Women have formerly been, they will
labour to imitate them in learning thoſe Arts their Sex hath invented, in
ſtudying thoſe Tongues they have underſtood, and in practiſing thoſe
Virtues ſhadowed under their Shapes; the knowledge of Arts<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64990:12"/>and Tongues, the exerciſe of Virtue and Piety, will certainly (let
men ſay what they will) make them honourable.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Care ought to be taken by us to Educate Women in
Learning.</head>
               <p>THat I may be more diſtinct in what I intend, I ſhall
diſtinguiſh of Women,</p>
               <p>Women are of two ſorts, 
<list>
                     <item>RICH, Of good natural Parts.</item>
                     <item>POOR, Of low Parts.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p> I do not mean, that it is neceſſary to the
<hi>eſſe,</hi> to the <hi>ſubſiſtence,</hi> or to the Salvation of
Women, to be thus educated. Thoſe that are mean in the World, have not an
opportunity for this Education: Thoſe that are of low Parts, though they have
opportunity, cannot reach this; <hi>Ex quovis ligno non ſit Minerva:</hi> My
meaning is, Perſons that God hath bleſſed with the things of this World,
that have competent natural Parts, ought to be educated in Knowledge; That is,
it is much better they ſhould ſpend the time of their Youth, to be
competently inſtructed in thoſe things uſually taught to Gentlewoman at
Schools, and the overplus of their time to be ſpent in gaining Arts, and
Tongues, and uſeful Knowledge, rather than to trifle away ſo many precious
minutes meerly to poliſh their Hands and Feet, to curl their Locks, to
dreſs and trim their Bodies; and in the mean time to neglect their Souls, and
not at all, or very little to endeavour to know God, Jeſus Chriſt,
Themſelves, and the things of Nature, Arts and Tongues, ſubſervient to
theſe. I do not deny but Women ought to be brought up to a comely and decent
carriage, to their Needle, to Neatneſs, to underſtand all thoſe things
that do particularly belong to their Sex. But when theſe things are
competently cared for, and where there are Endowments of Nature and leaſure,
then higher things ought to be endeavoured after. Meerly to teach Gentlewomen
to Frisk and Dance, to paint their Faces, to curl their Hair, to put on a
Whisk, to wear gay Clothes, is not truly to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn, but to adulterate their
Bodies; yea, (what is worſe) to defile their Souls. This (like
<hi>Circes</hi> Cup) turns them to Beaſts; whilſt their Belly is their
Godd, they become Swine; whilſt Luſt, they become Goats; and whilſt Pride
is their God, they become very Devils. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs this under-breeding of
Women began amongſt Heathen and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous People; it continues with the
<hi>Indians,</hi> where they make their Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64990:12"/>meer
ſlaves, and wear them out in drudgery. It is practiſed amongſt degenerate
and Apoſtate Chriſtians, upon the ſame ſcore, and now is a part of
their Religion; it would therefore be a piece of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to correct it;
and it would notably countermine them who fight againſt us, as Satan
againſt <hi>Adam,</hi> by ſeducing our Women, who then eaſily ſeduce
their Husbands.</p>
               <p>Had God intended Women onely as a finer ſort of Cattle, he
would not have made them reaſonable. Bruits, a few degrees higher than Drils
or Monkies, (which the <hi>Indians</hi> uſe to do many Offices) might have
better fitted ſome mens Luſt, Pride, and Pleaſure; eſpecially thoſe
that deſire to keep them ignorant to be tyrannized over.</p>
               <p>God intended Woman as a help-meet to Man, in his conſtant
conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and in the concerns of his Family and Eſtate, when he
ſhould moſt need, in ſickneſs, weakneſs, abſence, death,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whilſt we neglect to fit them for theſe things, we
renounce God's Bleſſing, he hath appointed Women for, are ungrateful to
him, cruel to them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to our ſelves.</p>
               <p>I remember a diſcourſe in <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> between an
Abbot and a learned Woman. She gives many good Reaſons why Women ſhould be
learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they might know God, their Saviour, underſtand his Sacred
Word, and admire him in his wonderful Works; that they might alſo better
adminiſter their Houſhold Affairs amongſt a multitude of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who
would have more reverence towards them, becauſe they were above them in
underſtanding. Further, ſhe found a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in reading good Authors
at ſpare times. He gives her one Anſwer to all this, <hi>That Women would
never be kept in ſubjection if they were learned;</hi> as he found by
experience amongſt his Monks, of all things in the World, he hated nothing
ſo much as a learned Monk, who would alwayes be contradicting his Superior,
from the Decretals out of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi> He cared not if all
his Monks were turned into Swine, ſo long as they would be obedient, and not
diſturb him in his Pleaſures. Doubtleſs if that generation of Sots (who
deny more Polite Learning to Women) would ſpeak out, they would tell you, If
Women ſhould be permitted Arts, they would be wiſer than themſelves (a
thing not to be endured) then they would never be ſuch tame fools and very
ſlaves as now they make them; therefore it is a wicked miſchievous thing to
revive the Ancient Cuſtom of Educating them.</p>
               <p>Seeing Nature produces Women of ſuch excellent Parts, that
they do often equalize, ſome-times excel men, in what ever they attempt; what
reaſon can be given why they ſhould not be improved?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64990:13"/>Nothing is more excellent than Man; his
excellency doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in his ſmooth Skin, or erect Countenance,
but in his Reaſonable Soul; and the excellency of Reaſon is, when it is
improved by Art.</p>
               <p>Learning perfects and adorns the Soul, which all Creatures aim
at. Nay more, a principal part of God's Image in Man's firſt Creation,
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in Knowledge. Sin hath clouded this: why ſhould we not by
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction endeavour to repair that which ſhall be perfected in
Heaven?</p>
               <p>None deny the underſtanding of the higheſt things belong to
Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; as, The knowledge of God, Meditation of his Word, Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his
Works; and they have been all along eminently employed in the great
Tranſactions of the Church: In the Old-Teſtament, <hi>Miriam, Debora, Jael,
Judith, Eſther.</hi> In the New-Teſtament, the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin,
<hi>Anna, Phebe, Priſcilla, Lois, Eunice,</hi> the Elect Lady,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> were all uſeful and ſerviceable to the Church. Who then
will forbid them the ſtudying of Arts, Tongues, Hiſtory, Philoſophy,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſubſervient to theſe? None can reverence the Majeſty
of God, nor admire his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Works, unleſs they in ſome meaſure know
him and them.</p>
               <p>This Nation was delivered from the <hi>Danes,</hi> by the
Valour, Secreſie, and Fidelity of the Women; and from worſe, than
<hi>Daniſh</hi> ſlavery by the means of a Woman.</p>
               <p>If any deſire diſtinctly to know what they ſhould be
inſtructed in?</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, I cannot tell where to begin to admit Women, nor
from what part of Learning to exclude them, in regard of their Capacities. The
whole <hi>Encyclopedeia</hi> of Learning may be uſeful ſome way or other to
them. Reſpect indeed is to be had to the Nature and Dignity of each Art and
Science, as they are more or leſs ſubſervient to Religion, and may be
uſeful to them in their ſtation. I would not deny them the knowledge of
Grammar and Rhetorick, becauſe they diſpoſe to ſpeak handſomly.
Logick muſt be allowed, becauſe it is the Key to all Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. Phyſick,
eſpecially Viſibles, as Herbs, Plants, Shrubs, Drugs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
muſt be ſtudyed, becauſe this will exceedingly pleaſe themſelves, and
fit them to be helpful to others. The Tongues ought to be ſtudyed,
eſpecially the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> theſe will enable to the
better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>The Mathematicks, more eſpecially Geography, will be uſeful;
this puts life into Hiſtory. Muſick, Painting, Poetry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are
a great or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament and pleaſure. Some things that are more practical, are not
ſo material, becauſe publick Employments in the Field and Courts, are
u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually denyed to Women: Yet ſome have not been inferior to many men even
in theſe things alſo. Witneſs <hi>Semiramis</hi> amongſt the
<hi>Babylonians;</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:64990:13"/>The Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> in
<hi>Arabia; Miriam</hi> and <hi>Debora</hi> among the <hi>Iſrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites;
Katherine de Medices</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> Queen <hi>Eliſabeth</hi> in
<hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> tells us of divers Women that have,
with good ſucceſs and great applauſe, pleaded their own Cauſes, as
<hi>Ameſia Sent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia;</hi> and <hi>Hortenſia</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Q.
Hortenſius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amaleſuentha,</hi> Queen of the Gothick Empire in
<hi>Italy,</hi> contempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> was exceedingly valued
by him; as appears by his Epiſtles recorded by <hi>Caſſiadorus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zenobia</hi> made the Countrey famous by her Learning and
Prudence.</p>
               <p>In theſe late Times there are ſeveral inſtances of Women,
when their Husbands were ſerving their King and Countrey, defended their
Houſes, and did all things, as Souldiers, with Prudence and Valour, like
Men.</p>
               <p>They appeared before Committees, and pleaded their own Cauſes
with good ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>This kind of Education will be very uſeful to Women.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The profit will be to themſelves. In the general they
will be able to underſtand, read, write, and ſpeak their Mother-Tongue,
which they cannot well do without this. They will have ſomething to
exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their thoughts about, which are buſie and active. Their quality
ties them at home; if Learning be their Companion, Delight and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure will
be their Attendants: for there is no pleaſure greater, nor more ſutable to
an ingenious mind, than what is founded in Knowledge; it is the firſt Fruits
of Heaven, and a glymps of that Glory we afterwards expect. There is in all an
innate deſire of knowing, and the ſatisfying this is the greateſt
pleaſure. Men are very cruel that give them leave to look at a diſtance,
only to know they do not know; to make any thus to tantalize, is a great
torment.</p>
               <p>This will be a Hedge againſt Hereſies. Men are furniſhed
with Arts and Tongues for this purpoſe, that they may ſtop the mouths of
their Adverſaries. And Women ought to be Learned, that they may ſtop their
ears againſt Seducers. It cannot be imagined ſo many Perſons of Quality
would be ſo eaſily carried aſide with every wind of Doctrine, had they
been furniſhed with theſe defenſive Arms; I mean, had they been
inſtructed in the plain rules of artificial reaſoning, ſo as to
diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh a true and forcible Argument, from a vain and captious
Fallacy. Had they been furniſhed with Examples of the moſt frequent
illuſions of erronious Seducers. <hi>Hereſiarks</hi> creep into Houſes,
and lead ſilly Women captive, then they lead their Husbands, both their
Children; as the Devil did <hi>Eve,</hi> ſhe her Husband, they their
Poſterity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:64990:14"/>It is none of the leaſt conſiderations,
that a Woman thus educated, who modeſtly uſes her Learning, is, in
deſpight of envy, honoured by moſt, eſpecially wiſe and good men;
ſuch a one is admired and even adored by the vulgar and illiterate.</p>
               <p>More particularly, perſons of higher quality, for want of this
Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, have nothing to imploy themſelves in, but are forced to Cards,
Dice, Playes, and frothy Romances, meerly to drive away the time; whereas
knowledge in Arts and Tongues would pleaſantly imploy them, and upon
occaſion benefit others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> endeavouring to comfort his Mother
<hi>Helvigia</hi> in her Affliction, when he was under Baniſhment,
ſuggeſts to her, that ſhe had been li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally brought up, and might now
have an opportunity to be farther improved, and might comfort her ſelf in the
ſtudy of Philoſophy.</p>
               <p>We cannot be ſo ſtupid as to imagine, that God gives Ladies
great Eſtates, meerly that they may Eat, Drink, Sleep, and riſe up to Play.
Doubtleſs they ought not to live thus. God, that will take an account for
every idle thought, will certainly reckon with thoſe Perſons that ſhall
ſpend their whole lives in idle play and chat. Poor Women will make but a
lame excuſe at the laſt day for their vain lives; it will be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
to ſay, that they were educated no better. But what Anſwer Men will make,
that do induſtriouſly deny them better improvement, leſt they ſhould be
wiſer than themſelves, I cannot imagine.</p>
               <p>More particularly, Women are 
<list>
                     <item>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmarried.</item>
                     <item>Married.</item>
                     <item>Widows.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>As for Unmarried Perſons, who are able to ſubſiſt
without a depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, they have a fairer opportunity than Men, if they
continue long in that eſtate, to improve the Principles they have ſucked
in, and to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Seeds of Learning which have been ſown in their minds
in their tender years. Beſides, this will be an honeſt and profitable
diverſion to poſſeſs their minds, to keep out worſe thoughts. Maids
that cannot ſubſiſt without depending, as Servants, may chuſe their
places, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon honourable Perſons, or to be imployed in Nurſeries;
by their Converſation, to team Tongues to Children, whilſt carried in Arms;
who perhaps, when they find their own feet, will not abide the <hi>tedium</hi>
of a School.</p>
               <p>The famous Lord <hi>Mountagn</hi> was thus improved, to the
amazement of all, which made him ever after hate all Pedantick Education.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64990:14"/>
                  <hi>Julius Ceſar</hi> alſo received
ſuch a tincture, whilſt he was in the Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, that he was the reviver
of the purity of the Latin Tongue in his dayes.</p>
               <p>Married Perſons, by vertue of this Education, may be very
uſeful to their Husbands in their Trades, as the Women are in
<hi>Holland;</hi> and to their Children, by timely inſtructing them, before
they are fit to be ſent to School; as was the caſe of <hi>Ceſar</hi> and
the Lord <hi>Mountagn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I need not ſhew how any Perſons, thus brought up, if they
happen to be Widows, will be able to underſtand and manage their own
Affairs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Women thus educated, will be beneficial to their
Relations. It is a great bleſſing of God to a Family, to provide a good
Wife for the Head, if it be eminent; and a preſage of ruine, when he ſends
a ranting <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebel</hi> to a ſoft <hi>Ahab.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One <hi>Athaliah,</hi> married to <hi>Joram,</hi> plucks ruine
upon the Houſe of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſaphat.</hi> How many Families have been ruined
by this one thing, the bad education of Women? Becauſe the Men find no
ſatisfactory con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe or entertainment at home, out of meer wearineſs
they ſeek abroad; hence they neglect their Buſineſs, ſpend their
Eſtates, deſtroy their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and oftentimes damn their Souls.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Italians</hi> ſlight their Wives, becauſe all
neceſſary knowledge, that may make them ſerviceable (attainable by
inſtitution) is denyed them: but they court, adore, and glory in their
Curtezans, though common Whores; becauſe they are poliſhed with more
generous breeding.</p>
               <p>Many learned Men, having married Wives of excellent Parts, have
themſelves inſtructed them in all kinds of Learning, the more to fit them
for their Converſe, and to indear them and their ſociety to them, and to
make them admired by others. The Woman is the glory of the Man; we joy in our
Children when eminent, and in our Wives when excellent, either in Body or
Mind.</p>
               <p>I have ſaid before how they may improve their Children in
Learning, eſpecially the Tongues; I mention it again, becauſe it is a
reaſon of ſo great weight, that it is ſufficient (if there was nothing
elſe) to turn the Scale. <hi>Tullia</hi> had never been ſo eloquent, had
not ſhe had ſo learned a Mother as <hi>Hortenſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Gracchi, Baptiſta, Damar, Ariſtippus,
Euſtochium</hi> (before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) had never been ſo famous in Arts and
Tongues, had they not been timely taught by their Mothers, <hi>Cornelia,
Conſtantia, Arete,</hi> and <hi>Paula.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:64990:15"/>King <hi>Lemuel</hi>'s Wiſdom was
extraordinary, yet he acknowledges the Seeds were ſown by the timely
inſtruction of his Mother, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. Therefore <hi>Solomon</hi>
charges Children to mind the Inſtruction of their Mothers; having found ſo
much good by it himſelf.</p>
               <p>Beſides, none have ſo great an advantage of making moſt
deep im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on their Children, as Mothers. What a prudent and virtuous
Mother commends by Precept and Example, ſticks long; witneſs
<hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> and his Proverbs, many of which he ſuckt in with his Mothers
Milk.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Timothy</hi> was taught the Holy Scriptures from a Child, by
his Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother <hi>Lois,</hi> and by his Mother <hi>Eunice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We may preſume the Children of the Elect Lady, were found
walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Truth from their Mothers Inſtructions. For they ſeldom
ſpeake the Language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> whoſe Mothers are of
<hi>Aſhdod.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Women thus inſtructed will be beneficial to the
Nation. Look into all Hiſtory, thoſe Nations ever were, now are, and
alwayes ſhall be, the worſt of Nations, where Women are moſt undervalued;
as in <hi>Ruſſia, Ethiopia,</hi> and all the Barbarous Nations of the
World. One great Reaſon why our Neighbours the <hi>Dutch</hi> have thriven to
admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is the great care they take in the Education of their Women, from
whence they are to be accounted more vertuous, and to be ſure more uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
than any Women in the World. We cannot expect otherwiſe to prevail againſt
the Ignorance, Atheiſm, Propnaneneſs, Superſtition, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, Luſt,
that reigns in the Nation, than by a Prudent, Sober, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Vertuous Education
of our Daughters. Their Learning would ſtir up our Sons, whom God and Nature
hath made ſuperior, to a juſt emulation.</p>
               <p>Had we a ſufficient number of Females thus inſtructed to
furniſh the Nurſeries of Noble Families, their Children might be improved
in the knowledge of the Learned Tongues before they were aware. I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this
a third time, becauſe it is of ſuch moment and concern.</p>
               <p>The memory of Queen <hi>Eliſabeth</hi> is yet freſh. By her
Learning ſhe was fitted for Government, and ſwayed the Scepter of this
Nation with as great honour as any man before her.</p>
               <p>Our very reformation of Religion, ſeems to be begun and
carried on by Women.</p>
               <p>Mris. <hi>Ann Askue,</hi> a Perſon famous for Learning and
Piety, ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned the Queen, and Ladies at Court, by her Precepts and
Examples, and after ſealed her Profeſſion with her Blood, that the Seed
of Reformation ſeemed to be ſowed by her hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64990:15"/>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth made a beginning
out of State Policy, his Femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine Relations acted out of true Piety; this
ſtuck in the Birth till his Daughter Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> carried it to
the height it is now at.</p>
               <p>My deſign is not to ſay all that may be ſaid in the
praiſe of Women. How modeſt and chaſt many have been; how remarkable in
their love to their Husbands, how conſtant in Religion, how dutiful to their
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, or how beneficial to their Countrey.</p>
               <p>The Scripture mentions the wiſe Woman at <hi>Abel,</hi> who
ranſomed the City from <hi>Joab</hi>'s Sword with <hi>Sheba</hi>'s Head, when
all the men were in a maze and knew not what to do. <hi>Debora</hi> was more
inſtrumental to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver <hi>Iſrael</hi> than <hi>Barak. Nabal</hi> and his
Houſe had been deſtroyed, had not <hi>Abigail</hi> wiſely pacified
<hi>David.</hi> The whole People of the <hi>Jews</hi> had been cut off, had not
<hi>Heſter</hi> adventured her life at the feet of <hi>Abaſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My intention is not to equalize Women to Men, much leſs to
make them ſuperior. They are the weaker Sex, yet capable of impreſſions
of great things, ſomething like to the beſt of Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hercules</hi> and <hi>Theſeus</hi> were very valiant;
<hi>Manalippe</hi> and <hi>Hyppolite</hi> were little inferior to them.
<hi>Zeuxes</hi> and <hi>Timanthes</hi> were brave Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. So were
<hi>Timarete, Irene, Lala, Martia,</hi> and many others.</p>
               <p>For Poetry, <hi>Sappho</hi> may be compared with <hi>Anacreon;
Corinna</hi> with <hi>Pindar. Tullia</hi> was eloquent like <hi>Cicero.
Cato</hi>'s Daughter little infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to himſelf in the Theory and Practice
of Philoſophy. <hi>Semiramis</hi> was like <hi>Alexander</hi> in
magnificence. The <hi>Tanaquils</hi> as politick as <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius Tullius.</hi>
The <hi>Porcea</hi>'s were as magnanimous as <hi>Brutus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The inference I make from hence is, that Women are not ſuch
ſilly giddy creatures, as many proud ignorant men would make them; as if they
were uncapable of all improvement by Learning, and unable to digeſt Arts,
that require any ſolidity of Judgment. Many men will tell you, they are ſo
unſtable and unconſtant, born down upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions with ſuch a
torrent of Fear, Love, Hatred, Luſt, Pride, and all manner of exorbitant
Paſſions, that they are uncapable to practiſe any Vertues, that require
greatneſs of Spirit, or firmneſs of Reſolution. Let ſuch but look into
Hiſtory, they will find Examples enow of illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Women to confute
them.</p>
               <p>Before I mention the Objections, I ſhall ſtate the
Propoſitions I have endeavoured to prove; That which I intend is this, That
Perſons of competent natural parts, indifferently inclin'd and diſpoſed
to Learning, whom God hath bleſſed with Eſtates, that they are not
cumbred in the World, but have liberty and opportunity in their Childhood; and
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards,<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64990:16"/>being competently inſtructed in all things
now uſeful that concern them as Women, may and ought to be improved in more
Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite Learning, in Religion, Arts, and the knowledge of things, in Tongues
alſo as ſubſervient to theſe, rather then to ſpend the over-plus time
of their youth, in making Points for Bravery, in dreſſing and trimming
themſelves like <hi>Bartholomew</hi>-Babies, in Painting and Dancing, in
making Flowers of Coloured Straw, and building Houſes of ſtained Paper, and
ſuch like vanities.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>No Body means Gentlewomen ſhould be thus educated
in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of meer vanity; but in practiſing their Needle, in knowing and
doing thoſe things that concern good Houſewifery, which is Womens
particular qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I know not what may be meant, but I ſee what
is generally done. In moſt Schools for educating this Sex, little more is
propoſed by the Undertakers, or expected by the Parents. As far as I can
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, the leſs any thing of ſolidity is taught, the more ſuch
places are frequented. I do acknowledge, in the ſtate of the Queſtion, that
Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould be accompliſhed in all thoſe things that concern them as
Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. My meaning is, The over-plus time may be imployed in poliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their
minds with the knowledge of ſuch things as may be honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, pleaſant and
profitable to them, and their Relations afterwards.</p>
               <p>Before I proceed further to Anſwer the remaining Objections, I
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire this may be taken notice of, That what-ever is ſaid againſt this
manner of Educating Women, may commonly be urged againſt the Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of
Men.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>If we bring up our Daughters to Learning, no
Perſons will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to Marry them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Many men, ſilly enough, (God knows)
think themſelves wiſe, and will not dare to marry a wiſe Woman, leſt
they ſhould be over-topt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As ſome Husbands, debauched themſelves, deſire
their Wives ſhould be chaſt, and their Children vertuous: So ſome men,
ſenſible of their own want, (cauſed by their Parents neglect) will
chuſe a learned Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, in whom they may glory, and by whoſe prudence their
defect may be ſupplyed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Learned men, to be ſure, will chuſe ſuch the
rather, becauſe they are ſutable. Some Men marrying Wives of good natural
parts, have improved themſelves in Arts and Tongues, the more to fit them for
their converſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Many Women formerly have been preferred for this very
thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:64990:16"/>
                  <hi>Athenais,</hi> Daughter to
<hi>Leontius</hi> the Philoſopher, left deſtitute by him, was entertained
by his Siſter <hi>Placida</hi> for her Learning, and was after married to the
Emperor <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> charmed by her worth, being fitted by her
education for that high place; ſhe is recorded for an excellent Empreſs.
Upon her being baptized, ſhe was called <hi>Eudocea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſtantine</hi> married <hi>Helena</hi> the Daughter of
<hi>Lois,</hi> more for her Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than any other accompliſhments.</p>
               <p>We may probably imagine <hi>Hortenſia, Terentia, Tullia,</hi>
and divers others, had never been married to ſuch brave men, had not their
Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation preferred them.</p>
               <p>If this way of educating Gentlewomen ſhould now be ſet on
foot, there will not be ſo great a number bred; but (as degenerate as times
are) there would be found learned men enow, to whom they may be preferred for
their very Education.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>It is againſt cuſtom to Educate Gentlewomen
thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Bad cuſtoms ought to be broken, or elſe
many good things would never come into uſe. I have ſhewed this is a
Heatheniſh Cuſtom, or a worſe, continued amongſt us upon very bad
grounds.</p>
               <p>Object. Solomon<hi>'s good Houſewife is commended for riſing
early, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying her Servants, making Garments, by which her Husband was known
in the Gate. It ſeems ſhe was of quality, ſhe had ſo many Servants, and
her Husband a Magiſtrate; their Courts of Judicature were at the Gate: no
mention is made of Arts or Tongues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It ſeems Perſons of Quality were more
induſtrious in thoſe times than they are now. I do not intend to hinder
good Houſe-wifery, neither have I called any from their neceſſary Labour
to their Book. My deſign is upon ſuch Perſons whoſe leaſure is a
burthen.</p>
               <p>Further, if <hi>Solomon</hi>'s good Houſe-wife was
accompliſhed with Arts and Tongues, ſhe would have more reverence from her
Servants, and by her knowledge in Economicks, know better how to manage ſo
great a Family.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> deſcribes an induſtrious Woman. I am
ſuggeſting what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ought to do that are about theſe things.
Thoſe that deny this, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve no Anſwer, but are to be thought on with
ſcorn, as that Duke that thought Women wiſe enough that knew their Husbands
Doublet and Breeches aſunder.</p>
               <p>If there be any perſons ſo vain, and are yet pleaſed with
this Apiſh kind of Breeding now in uſe, that deſire their Daughters
ſhould be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly dreſſed like Puppets, rather than inwardly adorned
with Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, let them enjoy their humour; but never wonder if ſuch
Marmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64990:17"/>married to Buffoons, bring forth and breed up a
generation of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boons, that have little more wit than Apes and Hobby-Horſes.
I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay enough againſt this Barbarous rudeneſs, to ſuffer one
part, I had almoſt ſaid the better part, of our ſelves to degenerate (as
far as poſſible) into brutality.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Women are of ill Natures, and will abuſe their
Education: They will be proud, and not obey their Husbands; they will be
pragmatick, and boaſt of their Parts and Improvements. The ill Nature that is
in them, will become more wicked, the more wit you furniſh them
with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is the killing Objection, and every
thick-skull'd Fellow that babbles this out, thinks no <hi>Billingsgate</hi>
Woman can Anſwer it. I ſhall take the Objection in pieces.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They will abuſe Learning.</hi>] So do men; he is
egregiouſly ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that argues againſt the uſe of a neceſſary or
very convenient thing from the abuſe of it. By this Argument no men ſhould
be liberally brought up; ſtrong Drinks ſhould never be uſed any more in
the World, and a hundred ſuch like things.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>They are of ill Natures.</hi>] This is an impudent
calumny; as if the whole Sex of Women, or the greateſt part of them, had that
malice infuſed into their very Natures and Conſtitutions, that they are
ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily made worſe by that Education that makes Men generally better. 
<q> 
                     <l>— Ingenuas didiciſſe fideliter artes</l> 
                     <l>Emollit mores, nec ſinit eſſe feros.</l>
                  </q> The
Heathen found, that Arts wrought upon Men, the rougher Sex. Surely it is want
of fidelity in the Inſtructer, if it have not the like effect upon ſofter
and finer Materials.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>They will be proud, and not obey their
Husbands.</hi>] To this I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; What is ſaid of Philoſophy, is true of
Knowledge; a little Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy carries a Man from God, but a great deal
brings him back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; a little knowledge, like windy Bladders, puffs up, but
a good meaſure of true knowledge, like Ballaſt in a Ship, ſettles down,
and makes a perſon move more even in his ſtation; 'tis not knowing too
much, but too little that cauſes the irregularity. This ſame Argument may
be turned upon Men; what-ever they anſwer for themſelves, will defend
Woman.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that deſire a farther Anſwer, let them peruſe
<hi>Eraſmus</hi> his Dialogue, of the <hi>Ignorant Abbot</hi> and the
<hi>Learned Woman.</hi> An igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Magiſtrate, or Miniſter, may as well
plead againſt improvement<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64990:17"/>of Knowledge in all below them,
leſt they ſhould be wiſer than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo deride them. Do
not deny Women their due, which is to be as well inſtructed as they can; but
let Men do their duty, to be wiſer than they are. If this doth not pleaſe,
let ſilly Men let wiſe Women alone; the rule is, All ſhould be (as near
as they can) equally yoked.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>The end of Learning is publick Buſineſs, which
Women are not capable of. They muſt not ſpeak in the Church; and it is more
proper for men to Act in the Common-Wealth than they.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They may not ſpeak in the Church, but they
may inquire of their Husbands at home; it is private inſtruction I plead for,
not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Imployment. Yet there is no ſuch contradiction in the terms:
<hi>Miriam</hi> and <hi>Deborah</hi> were extraordinarily called forth by God,
as well as <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Barak.</hi> Sometimes Women may have
occaſions for publick Buſineſs, as Widows, and Wives when their Husbands
are abſent; but eſpecially perſons born to Government. The
<hi>Salique</hi> Law hath not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed all the World over, and good reaſon
too; for Women upon Thrones have been as glorious in their governing, as many
Men, as I have ſhewed before. But lay all this aſide; there are other ends
of Learning, beſides pleading in the Hall, and appearing in the Pulpit.
Private Perſons (as I have before ſhewed) may many ways pleaſe
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and benefit others. This Objection alſo will turn the Point
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Men that are in a private capacity.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>They will not mind their Houſhold
Affairs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Men are judged to be more capable of Countrey
buſineſs by liberal Education. Moſt ingenious Contrivances, even in
Husbandry and Trades, have been invented by Scholars. You may as well ſay, a
Gentleman that hath Countrey Affairs to manage, ought not to be a Scholar,
becauſe he will be poring upon his Book, when he ſhould be looking after
his Plowmen.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>They have other things to do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe which have, may mind thoſe things for
ought I have ſaid: The Queſtion is of perſons at leaſure, Whether
theſe had not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be imployed in ſome good Literature, than in pilling
Straws, or doing nothing, which is the certain Seed of doing miſchief?</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Women do not deſire Learning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Neither do many Boys, (as Schools are now
ordered) yet I ſuppoſe you do not intend to lay Fallow all Children that
will not bring forth Fruit of themſelves, to forbear to inſtruct thoſe
which at preſent do not thank you for it.</p>
               <p>But I have ſaid, there is in all an innate deſire of
knowing, in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64990:18"/>as well as Men: if the wayes to the
Temple of <hi>Pallas</hi> be ſo tedious and intricate, that they confound or
tire her Servants; or, if you dreſs up Learning in ſuch an ugly and
monſtrous ſhape, that you afright Children; I have nothing to ſay to
ſuch, but that they ſhould reform their Schools, or elſe all will think
they have no deſire any, either Male or Female, ſhould be inſtructed.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Women are of low Parts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> So are many Men; we plead only for thoſe
which have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Parts. To be ſure, ſome Women are as capable of
Learning, and have attained to as great height in it as moſt Men; witneſs
thoſe Examples before produced.</p>
               <p>If this be true, their Parts generally are lower than Mens,
there is the more need they ſhould by all convenient means be improved.
Crutches are for infirm perſons.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Women are of ſofter Natures, more delicate and
tender Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, not ſo fixed and ſolid as Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If their Natures are ſoft, they are more
capable of good Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions; if they are weak, more ſhame for us to
neglect them, and defraud them of the benefit of <hi>Education,</hi> by which
they may be ſtrengthened.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>It is againſt cuſtom to educate Gentlewomen
thus; thoſe that do attempt it, will make themſelves ridiculous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Argument might have been uſed to the
<hi>Iriſh;</hi> not to uſe Traces at Plow and Cart, but to draw their
Horſes by their Tails, which was a general cuſtom amongſt them. Bad
Cuſtoms (when it is evident they are ſo) ought to be broken, or elſe good
Cuſtoms can never come into uſe. That this is a bad Cuſtom, is evident,
continued upon a bad ground. Let Women be Fools, and then you may eaſily make
them Slaves.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>What need Women learn Tongues, there are Books enow
in Engliſh for them to peruſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The great Thing I deſign is, the Knowledge of
things; as Religion, the Names and Natures of Herbs, Shrubs, Trees,
Mineral-Juyces, Metals, and Precious Stones; as alſo the Principles of Arts
and Sciences before mentioned. The learning of Tongues is only ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient
to theſe. Was all Learning in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as it is now in
<hi>French,</hi> I think thoſe dead Languages would be of little uſe, only
in reference to the Scriptures. My opinion is, in the Educating of Gentlewomen,
greater care ought to be had to know things, than to get words. If one 
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64990:18"/>muſt be neglected, it's better to neglect Tongues than
Arts; though it is beſt where both may be had.</p>
               <p>Object. Solomon<hi>'s vertuous Woman,</hi> Prov. 31. <hi>is
commended for good Houſewifery, not for Arts and Tongues; yet her Husband was
a Perſon of Quality, he ſat amongst the Elders of the Land in the
Gate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It ſeems Perſons of Quality were more
induſtrious in thoſe times than now they are. Our Ladies would count it a
great diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to them to do as ſhe did; to ſeek Wool and Flax, and
to work willingly with their own hands, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. to lay their hands
to the Spindle, and to take hold on the Diſtaff, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. to
riſe while it is Night, and to give Meat to her Houſhold, and a Portion to
her Maids, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. It's like the neceſſities of thoſe times
were greater, and the way of living far different from that which is now in
uſe. The Duke of <hi>Florence</hi> is a great Merchant; Noblemen in
<hi>England,</hi> and Gentlemen in <hi>France,</hi> think it diſparagement to
them to be ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. I plead that our Ladies ſhould have but
the ſame Abilities this vertuous Woman had; not to labour as ſhe did, but
to underſtand as ſhe did. I am ſure to do all thoſe things well that
ſhe performed, ſo as to be reverenced of her Servants, that her Children
ſhould riſe up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her, and call her Bleſſed, and that her Husband
ſhould praiſe her, requires knowledge in Arts and Sciences, which were
hardly got in thoſe dayes without the knowledge of Tongues; if they then
were, or can be now, I am contented without them.</p>
               <p>To buy Wooll and Flax, to die Scarlet and Purple, requires skill
in Natural Philoſophy. To conſider a Field, the quantity and quality,
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires knowledge in Geometry. To plant a Vineyard, requires under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
in Husbandry: She could not Merchandize, without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Arithmetick: She
could not govern ſo great a Family well, without knowledge in Politicks and
Oeconomicks: She could not look well to the wayes of her Houſhold, except
ſhe underſtood Phyſick and Chirurgery: She could not open her Mouth with
Wiſdom, and have in her Tongue the Law of kindneſs, unleſs ſhe
underſtood Grammar, Rhetorick and Logick. This ſeems to be the
deſcription of an honeſt, well-bred, ingenious, induſtrious Dutch-woman.
I deſire our Women (whoſe condition calls them to buſineſs) ſhould
have no other breeding, but what will enable to do thoſe things performed by
this Woman.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe that are above theſe, I am ſure the higheſt
breeding ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable will be uſeful to them. I believe the men of our times
would ſay, it's pitty any Woman ſhould have ſo much Authority as this
Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64990:19"/>had, ſhe would be ſo maſterly there would be no
living with her.</p>
               <p>Object. Another Objection that ſeems unanſwerable, is this;
<hi>How ſhall time be found to teach Children theſe things here propoſed?
Boyes go to School ordinarily from ſeven till ſixteen or ſeventeen, and
not above one in four attain ſo much knowledge in the Tongues; as to be
admitted into the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, where no great accuracy is required; and they
learn nothing elſe uſually, beſides a little Hiſtory: Gentlewomen will
not ordinarily be ſent out ſo ſoon, nor is it convenient they ſhould
continue ſo long. Further, half their time, it is ſuppoſed, muſt be
ſpent in learning thoſe things that concern them as Women. Twice as many
things are propoſed to be taught Girls in half the time, as Boyes do learn,
which is impoſſible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Objection makes the whole Contrivance
ſeem idle, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a ſatisfactory Anſwer be given.</p>
               <p>I ſay therefore, The learning of things will be no hinderance
to the getting Words. Words are the marks of things, and they are learnt better
together than aſunder. As a man ſhall ſooner remember Names, if he ſee
the perſons, ſo a Girl ſhall much eaſier faſten in her memory the
names of Herbs, Shrubs, Mineral-Juyces, Metals, Precious Stones; as alſo the
names of Birds, Beaſts, Fiſhes; the parts of Man's Body; if ſhe ſee the
things themſelves in <hi>ſpecie;</hi> or the Pictures and
Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, where the things themſelves cannot be had. This is a
great Truth, (if there be any ſuch thing as a concatenation of Notions, as
doubtleſs there is) the thing being perceived, Words freely follow.
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, to learn words thus, will be very pleaſant and delightful, even
to Children. As the eye is not ſatisfied with ſeeing, if it be an Object it
can reach and diſtinguiſh: So the mind of a Child is not ſatisfied with
underſtanding, if it be a thing he can apprehend. Let thoſe that do believe
this, try a Child of four years old in plain Pictures of Men, Beaſts, Birds,
or Fiſhes, they will ſee how inquiſitive he will be; or, let them ſhew
Herbs, Flowers, Stones, or any thing rare, and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is any burthen
to the Childs underſtanding or memory to learn the name when he ſees the
thing.</p>
               <p>Let no Body be afrighted, becauſe ſo many things are to be
learnt, when the learning of them will be ſo pleaſant; how profitable I
need not tell you.</p>
               <p>If any doubt how this may be done, or what Authors we ſhall
uſe, that words and things may be learnt together;</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, <hi>Comenius</hi> hath prepared
<hi>Nomenclatures</hi> for this purpoſe. His<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64990:19"/>
                  <hi>Orbis
Pictus,</hi> contains all the Primitive Latine words, and the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
of moſt things capable of being ſet out by Pictures; it may be learnt by
beginners in three months, and is as a Syſtem of his <hi>Janua
Linguarum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Janna Linguarum,</hi> a Syſtem of things,
conſiſts of a thouſand Sentences; ten of which may be learnt in one day,
fifty in a week, the thouſand in twenty-ſix weeks; allowing one day in a
week, and one week in a month for Repetition, that we may keep what we get.
Thus nine months is ſpent, I mean by Gentlewoman, that ſpend but ſix
hours in a day at their Books; the other three months may be imployed in
gaining the <hi>French</hi> Tongue, which I thus demonſtrate.</p>
               <p>If the Latin <hi>Janua</hi> may be learnt in ſix months, where
moſt of the words are new, then the <hi>French</hi> may be learnt in three,
by one that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Latin;</hi> becauſe
there is not above one word of ten in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue, that may not
fairly, without force, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the <hi>Latin</hi> or
<hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe two new Languages being learnt, one will help to keep
the other. This I propoſe may be done to a Gentlewoman of nine or ten years
old, that is of good Capacity; lower Parts require longer time.</p>
               <p>If we ſhould dance that wild-Gooſe-chaſe uſually led, it
would require longer time; ordinarily Boys learn a Leaf or two of the
<hi>Pueriles,</hi> twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Pages of <hi>Corderius,</hi> a part of <hi>Eſop's
Fables,</hi> a piece of <hi>Tullie,</hi> a little of <hi>Ovid,</hi> a remnant
of <hi>Virgil, Terence,</hi> &amp;c. and when all this is done, they have not
much above half ſo many words as this little <hi>Enchiridion,</hi> the
<hi>Janua,</hi> ſupplies them with.</p>
               <p>It's true, this courſe inſtructs us only in the propriety of
the words; therefore it is ſo much the better, it's the univerſal proceſs
of Nature to riſe by degrees, to proceed from Seeds to Leaves, from Leaves to
Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; from plain things to things ornamental. One would think thoſe
learned Men mad, that go quite contrary to this Proceſs; that propoſe to
ſeaſon with Rhetorick, and a ſtile, by reading crabbed Claſſick
Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, as <hi>Terence,</hi> &amp;c. before Children underſtand any thing
of the plain ſignification of words.</p>
               <p>But, methinks, I hear my Reader complain that I abuſe him: I
hear him confeſs this is but reaſon; But he thinks I ſhun the difficulty,
and ſay nothing to <hi>Grammar,</hi> the ground-work of all; to begin at
<hi>In Speech,</hi> to read the <hi>Accidence,</hi> and to get it without Book,
is ordinarily the work of one whole year.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:64990:20"/>To Conſtrue the <hi>Grammar,</hi> and to
get it without-Book, is at leaſt the task of two years more; and then, it may
be, it is little under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, until a year or two more is ſpent in making
plain Latin. My Reader, it may be, thinks I have forgot, or purpoſely omitted
to allow time for theſe things, without which nothing can be done.</p>
               <p>I do confeſs, to proceed in <hi>Lilly</hi>'s Method, (as is
before mentioned) to commit the very <hi>Accidence</hi> and <hi>Grammar</hi> to
memory, requires three or four years, ſometimes more, (as many can witneſs
by woful experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) and when all is done, beſides <hi>declining Nouns,</hi>
and <hi>forming Verbs,</hi> and getting a few words, there is very little
advantage to the Child. This being ſuppoſed, it's not likely Children of
ordinary Parts ſhould in ſo ſhort a time be improved in any competent
meaſure in the Latin Tongue.</p>
               <p>The great reaſon of theſe Intricacies is, the whole Method
ſwerves from the Rules of true Didacticks.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This is an undenyable Principle; All Rules ought to be
plain, that they may be eaſily underſtood, eſpecially ſuch as are to be
learnt by Children, to the meanneſs of whoſe Capacities we ought to
conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend.</p>
               <p>The Rules in <hi>Lilly's Grammar</hi> are not ſo, becauſe
they are in Latin, a Tongue the Learner doth not underſtand; and which is
worſe, a great part of them is in verſe, hardly intelligible to a Child if
they are tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Grammatical Engliſh.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another undoubted Principle is; All Knowledge is
increaſed by <hi>Syncriſis,</hi> (comparing one thing with another) whoever
would beget a new <hi>Idea</hi> in any ones underſtanding, reduces it (if
poſſible) to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing he knows already, that is like it. This is a Law
of Nature, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever proceeds according to it, moves ſmoothly, as an oyled
Clock when the Wheels are put into their right places. Who-ever goes not
according to this Rule, forces Water upwards, which returns to its Channel,
ſo ſoon as the <hi>vis impreſſa</hi> is ſpent; his motion is like to
a Leg or an Arm out of joynt, very uneaſie.</p>
               <p>Much of the Method uſed in <hi>Lilly's Grammar,</hi> in the
<hi>Etymologia,</hi> and the whole <hi>Syntax,</hi> that concerns Government,
varies from this grand Principle.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that would rationally teach Latin to a Child bred
amongſt us, ought to accommodate his Inſtruction to the Engliſh Tongue,
the Tongue ſhe knows already, and by <hi>Syncriſis,</hi> proceed
<hi>à noto ad ignotum.</hi> This would be eaſie and pleaſant; but
<hi>Lillies Grammar</hi> hath no more<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64990:20"/>reſpect to the
<hi>Engliſh,</hi> than to the <hi>Welſh</hi> or <hi>Iriſh.</hi> For
inſtance; <hi>A Noun is the name of a thing which may be ſeen, felt, heard,
or underſtood.</hi> A Man doth not underſtand this, when the <hi>Noun</hi>
is a ſecond Notion, or not obvious to ſenſe. Beſides, it may as well be
applyed to <hi>Welſh, Iriſh, Dutch, French, Italian,</hi> or
<hi>Spaniſh,</hi> as to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Noun.</p>
               <p>If you demand, <hi>How can a better Rule be given, which may be
more uſeful?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Anſwer;</hi> A <hi>Noun</hi> may have uſually before
it in the Engliſh, <hi>a, an,</hi> or <hi>the,</hi> as <hi>a Man, an Angel,
the Book.</hi> This every Child underſtands at the firſt naming.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lilly</hi> ſaith, <hi>A Subſtantive ſtands by it
ſelf, and requires not another word to ſhew its ſignification. An
Adjective cannot ſtand by it ſelf, but requires another word to ſhew its
ſignification.</hi> This is better than the former, yet hard enough for a
Child to underſtand. Take your indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and
ſee how plain it is. A <hi>Subſtantive</hi> varies in the number, as
<hi>Book, Books.</hi> An <hi>Adjective</hi> doth not vary in the number, as
<hi>good Book, good Books. Good</hi> is uſed both in the <hi>ſingular</hi>
and <hi>plural Number.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pronouns,</hi> in our old <hi>Grammar,</hi> are ſaid to be
<hi>parts of Speech much like to Nouns, uſed in Shewing or Rehearſing.</hi>
They are like to Nouns, that is, they are the names of things that may be
underſtood, and ſo like to <hi>Nouns</hi> in this, that I cannot know them
aſunder. Then <hi>Lilly</hi> reckons them up in <hi>Latin,</hi> but dares not
name them in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> leſt you ſhould know them too quickly. How
eaſily is this diſpatched, if we enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the <hi>Pronouns</hi> (let them
be what they will) in two Claſſes, thus; <hi>I, thou, he, we, ye,
they,</hi> are <hi>Subſtantives; my, thy, his, our, your,</hi> &amp;c. are
<hi>Adjectives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is better to tell a Child, <hi>Verbs</hi> have a ſign of a
<hi>Mood</hi> or <hi>Tenſe,</hi> than to ſay, they ſignifie <hi>doing,
ſuffering,</hi> or <hi>being.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Participles</hi> are wildly deſcribed to be <hi>Parts of
Speech,</hi> that take part of a <hi>Noun,</hi> and part of a <hi>Verb,</hi>
&amp;c. No child is at all edified by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition. I confeſs this part of
Speech is moſt difficult to be known in the Engliſh Tongue; yet it may be
done thus, All words ending in <hi>ing, d, t,</hi> or <hi>n,</hi> which have no
ſign at all, and may be reſolved into <hi>Verbs,</hi> are
<hi>Participles,</hi> as <hi>learning, which doth learn; learned, which is
learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we now look back, that great ſtumbling-block to
diſtinguiſh the parts of Speech, (which coſts years, before a Child
diſtinctly knows them, whilſt he looks upon them in their Latin dreſs) is
got over in a<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64990:21"/>few dayes, when we take our direction from our
own Tongue. I will repeat it again, that I may be perfectly underſtood.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Noun</hi> may have uſually before it in the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, <hi>a, an,</hi> or <hi>the. Subſtantives</hi> have
a different termination in the <hi>Number; Adjectives</hi> have not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pronouns</hi> are all enumerated about thirty; ſome are
<hi>Subſtantives,</hi> others are <hi>Adjectives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verbs</hi> may have a ſign of a <hi>Mood</hi> or
<hi>Tenſe.</hi> All words ending in <hi>ing, d, t,</hi> or <hi>n,</hi> which
have no ſign, and may be reſolved into <hi>Verbs,</hi> are,
<hi>Participles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prepoſitions</hi> are all enumerated, about thirty;
what-ever integral word is not <hi>Noun, Pronoun, Verb, Participle,</hi> or
<hi>Prepoſition,</hi> is either an <hi>Adverb,</hi> or a
<hi>Conjunction,</hi> it matters not much which a beginner calls them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Interjections</hi> are all virtual Sentences; a few dayes
will maſter this, if we proceed gradually.</p>
               <p>I do not know much more requiſite to Gentlewomen, that intend
not to be critical, beſides declining <hi>Nouns,</hi> and forming
<hi>Verbs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſpecial Rules for the <hi>genders</hi> of <hi>Nouns,</hi>
are but five, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions are not many.</p>
               <p>There are but three general Rules for that part of
<hi>Grammar</hi> called the <hi>As in praeſenti,</hi> the irregular
<hi>Verbs,</hi> which moſt frequently occur in Authors, in number about five
hundred, are learned as a <hi>Vocabulary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Syntax;</hi> the two firſt Concords only are of
uſe; and the Rules for Government, (eight ſcore in number in <hi>Lillies
Grammar</hi>) are competently accommodated to the ſigns of the
<hi>Caſes</hi> thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Subſtantives</hi> have their <hi>Caſes</hi> by the
<hi>Signs,</hi> and they are governed of the word going before, on which they
depend according to the ſigns <hi>of, to, for, with, from, by, then, in, at,
on, a, the.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Four exceptions ſubjoyned to this Rule, may make the
<hi>Syntax</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat enough for a Woman, that intends onely a
ſuperficial Knowledge in the Tongue; ten more exceptions (that concern onely
particular words) will make them, as profound as moſt men are by <hi>Lillies
Rules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To Anſwer the Objection fully; to know the parts of
<hi>Speech</hi> by theſe Rules; to decline a <hi>Noun,</hi> to form a
<hi>Verb,</hi> to digeſt the five gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rules, and five ſpecial Rules
for the genders of <hi>Nouns,</hi> to commit to memory the three grand Rules,
containing the <hi>As in praeſenti;</hi> to decline thoſe five hundred
irregular <hi>Verbs,</hi> to underſtand the two <hi>Concords,</hi> and that
one general Rule for Government, with four Exceptions, will not require many
months.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:64990:21"/>The Prefacer to <hi>Lillies Grammar</hi>
(who I hope is very authentick) tells you, more than this may be done very
accurately by thoſe blundering Rules of <hi>Lillie</hi> in the ſpace of
three months, by Children of mean parts.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that do not underſtand theſe ſhort hints, may
peruſe a <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> and an <hi>Apology;</hi> to which is added Rules
for Pointing and Reading Grammatically; Compoſed by M. <hi>Lewis,</hi> Sold
by <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Bible and three Crowns in
<hi>Cheapſide,</hi> in which theſe things are more largely diſcuſſed.
Or they may ſpeak with M. <hi>Lewis</hi> himſelf any <hi>Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi>
in the Afternoon, between three and ſix of the Clock, at the Bolt and Tun in
<hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will not trouble you with his Diſcourſe, how this Method
is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the general rule of Speaking, that goes through the World, and
how the Engliſh Tongue is one of the moſt regular Languages ſpoken upon
the face of the Earth. The <hi>Grammar</hi> of this being known, it may be a
Standard to meaſure all other Languages by.</p>
               <p>If you peruſe his <hi>Apologie,</hi> you will ſee how the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> is a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>Latin,</hi> the <hi>Latin</hi>
to the <hi>Greek,</hi> you may there ſee how he demonſtrates, to learn to
decline <hi>Greek Nouns,</hi> and form <hi>Greek Verbs,</hi> hath not a fourth
part of the difficulty in it, as there is in the <hi>Latin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let not Perſons raſhly cenſure theſe Propoſals, before
they have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined the <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> and heard what the Author can
ſay in defence of it.</p>
               <p>Let no Perſon be diſcouraged, becauſe Grammar, Words, and
Things, are propoſed to be learnt in ſo ſhort a time; the plainneſs and
ſhortneſs of the Grammar, the ſeeing the Things, and having the Words in
ſo ſhort a compaſs, will make the Work eaſie and very delightful.</p>
               <p>If all I have ſaid may conveniently be done, I expect many
will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride this Deſign. I am contented, let them abound in their own
ſenſe, and have Wives as ſilly as themſelves deſire, over whom they
may ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize.</p>
               <p>I hope I ſhall by this Diſcourſe perſwade ſome Parents
to be more careful for the future of the Breeding of their Daughters. You cark
and care to get great Portions for them, which ſometimes occaſions their
ruine. Here is a ſure Portion, an eaſie way to make them excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. How
many born to good Fortunes, when their Wealth hath been waſted, have
ſupported themſelves and Families too by their Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom?</p>
               <p>I hope ſome of theſe Conſiderations will at leaſt move
ſome of this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed Sex to ſet a right value upon themſelves,
according to the dignity<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64990:22"/>of their Creation, that they might,
with an honeſt pride and magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, ſcorn to be bowed down and made to
ſtoop to ſuch Follies and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, Trifles and Nothings, ſo far below
them, and unproportionable to their noble Souls, nothing inferior to thoſe of
Men, and equally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to God in Chriſt, in whom there is neither Male
nor Female.</p>
               <p>Let a generous reſolution poſſeſs your minds, ſeeing
Men in this Age have invaded Womens Vices, in a noble revenge, reaſſume
thoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, which Men ſometimes unjuſtly uſurped to themſelves,
but ought to have left them in common to both Sexes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>IF any enquire where this Education may be performed; ſuch may
be informed, That a <hi>School</hi> is lately erected for Gentlewomen at
<hi>Tottenham-high-Croſs,</hi> within four miles of <hi>London,</hi> in the
Road to <hi>Ware;</hi> where Mris. <hi>Makin</hi> is Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſs, who was
ſometimes Tutoreſs to the Princeſs <hi>Eliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> Daughter to
King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt; Where, by the bleſſing of God,
Gentlewomen may be inſtructed in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Religion;</hi> and in
all manner of Sober and Vertuous Education: More particularly, in all things
ordinarily taught in other Schools:</p>
            <p>As, 
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Works of all Sorts,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dancing,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Muſick,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Singing,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Writing,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Keeping Accompts,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>Half the time to be ſpent in theſe Things.</p>
            <p> The other half to be imployed in gaining the <hi>Latin</hi> and
<hi>French</hi> Tongues; and thoſe that pleaſe, may learn <hi>Greek</hi>
and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> the <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh:</hi> In all which
this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen hath a competent knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:64990:22"/>Gentlewomen of eight or nine years old, that
can read well, may be inſtructed in a year or two (according to their Parts)
in the <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Tougues; by ſuch plain and ſhort
Rules, accommodated to the <hi>Grammar</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue,
that they may eaſily keep what they have learned, and recover what they
ſhall loſe; as thoſe that learn Muſick by Notes.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that will beſtow longer time, may learn the other
Languages, afore-mentioned, as they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repoſitories</hi> alſo for Viſibles ſhall be prepared;
by which, from beholding the things, Gentlewomen may learn the Names, Natures,
Values, and Uſe of <hi>Herbs, Shrubs, Trees, Mineral-Juices, Metals</hi> and
<hi>Stones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that pleaſe, may learn <hi>Limning, Preſerving,
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry</hi> and <hi>Cookery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that will allow longer time, may attain ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
Knowledge in <hi>Aſtronomy, Geography;</hi> but eſpecially in
<hi>Arithmetick</hi> and <hi>Hiſtory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that think one Language enough for a Woman, may forbear
the Languages, and learn onely <hi>Experimental Philoſophy;</hi> and more, or
fewer of the other things afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, as they incline.</p>
            <p>The Rate certain ſhal be 20 <hi>l. per annum:</hi> But if a
compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent improvement be made in the Tongues, and the other things
aforementioned, as ſhall be agreed upon, then ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more will be
expected. But the Parents ſhall judge what ſhall be deſerved by the
Undertaker.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that think theſe Things Improbable or Impracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable,
may have further account every <hi>Tueſday</hi> at Mr. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>
Coffe-Houſe in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the Royal Exchange; and
<hi>Thurſdayes</hi> at the Bolt and Tun in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> between
the hours of three and ſix in the Afternoons, by ſome Perſon whom Mris.
<hi>Makin</hi> ſhall appoint.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
